hello I'm your host David Barnard and my
guest today is Matthew panzarino the
former editorinchief at TechCrunch on
the podcast I talk with Matthew about
how to pitch your app to the press the
importance of focusing on
differentiation and why customizing your
pitch to an individual writer is so much
more effective hey Matthew thanks so
much for joining me on the podcast today
thanks David I appreciate you having me
on yeah so I'm excited to talk through
you know you were at Tech crunch for 10
years and before that working at the
next web and have a lot of insights in
what it's like to be a writer who's
pitched hundreds of times a day but also
know how to tell great stories and how
to get attention for things so I want to
dive in just talking about what it's
like to be a writer in 2023 I think a
lot of folks don't quite understand just
how inundated folks email boxes are so
when they send out a pitch they don't
know that they're one of maybe hundreds
in a single day and they're expecting a
response but aren't crafting their pitch
in a way that helps get attention and so
let's just kick it off with that like
what is it like for your average Tech
crunch writer and you know so many other
people in the press as well but what's
it like in 2023 to be a tech journalist
yeah I mean it is tough you're right
like the fire hose thing is real there's
just an enormous amount if you look at
like the early days of the app store in
the 2010 2011 range I mean obviously app
store was launched a couple years prior
but didn't really start to gain steam
Beyond Boutique apps or early adopters
shipping apps until about the 2010 2011
range that was essentially when the
pendulum swung towards everybody must
have an app like oh you are a brand you
are a company you are an entity you
should have an app as well as of course
the new companies being founded turning
towards
oh you're founding a company that does a
thing on the internet why aren't you
doing it as an app that was the kind of
Turning Point at that time the volume
was very much manageable right it was
hey dozens of apps are launching every
week but we can scan those get a feel
for what's interesting maybe there's an
existing brand that is launching an app
presentence and so we're going to see
what their take on it is cuz at that
point you're charting in real time
charting the history of what it means to
make an app yeah what features it needs
what design looks like in that space Etc
I believe that's how you and I met when
you were at the next web I think it was
like a cold pitch at the next web in in
2010 2011 is when we first were talking
and it was it was genuinely easier back
then to get a hold of somebody like you
and have a conversation and talk about
your app yeah I mean I think those days
of hey I'm just a person who's trying to
do a thing and it's app related the app
part of it was enough to kind of go okay
cool it's an app thing let me look at it
see if there's anything that I think on
the first glance it seems compelling or
clever or stands out in some way like
they're leveraging a new piece of
framework that iOS is launching right
now obviously not everybody thinks this
way but as far as the core Tech press
which is really my only real perspective
on this I never really existed in the
longtale news rooms where it's like the
storytelling gets more nebulous around
does this TCH on a cultural moment is
there a celebrity involved does it tap
into another Zeitgeist that I already
cover that's different but for us at
that time specifically and frankly even
to this day it's like oh you're
leveraging a bit of new technology
that's been launched by the platform
whether it's like Apple or Google or
whoever else or you're leveraging a new
sensor a new piece of hardware and
you're saying like hey this makes this
experience possible it wasn't possible
before I think a lot of that stuff was
very easy in the early days to pick up
on and go oh okay cool this is clever it
seems interesting the person seems like
they have their stuff together it seems
welld designed because design is a
calling card as you and I both well know
it's the equivalent of a well-designed
business card is now your web presence
or your app if it looks clean crisp
welld designed well presented the copy
is Simple and Clean and spelled
correctly the font choices are good
these things are for someone who is
actively looking at an app and saying
should I cover this or should I not
every day you just sort of get a
sensibility about which of those are
going to be worth your attention out of
the hundreds of pitches that you may
receive in a day uh if you're flicking
through those you're like hey this
stands out for those reasons um but even
if you are not a student of app design
or a student of typography or anything
like that it is very much subc contan
it's there right whether you actively
realize it or not it's affecting you as
the viewer and so I think that's
important to remember putting your best
foot forward design-wise
or sidestepping that entirely and
generating curiosity based on lack of
information right that's also aack
because the fact is it's like to rein
ourselves in and bring it back to that
exact question about getting intention
and what it's like to be a writer you
have a few seconds per email at most to
make any judgment call about whether or
not you're going to engage with it and
I'm talking about whether or not you're
going to click through from the subject
line some people are crazy and work with
their inbox on an expanded basis for me
it's sender and subject line that's the
most I can afford real estate wise you
other writers work differently so this
is not a mandate it's not how everybody
works but most of the people I know work
this way and so your subject line needs
to be simple it needs to either be very
short or very long in other words are
you putting everything in the subject
line and the body is basically just
here's the contact information or here's
a link to a press kit or are you trying
to say please look at this because XYZ
very short very simple and then get in
there and then make your pitch in the
copy so there's two major approaches I
feel that work very well for a writer
who's scanning subject lines so your
subject line maybe gets in the major
keywords which should not by the way for
the most part be hinged on public
affairs I just don't feel that public
affairs pitching works well that's news
hook pitching which I think a lot of PR
agencies will tell you to do and think
is very useful I don't in general find
it very useful and I think most writers
unfortunately tend to be more skeptical
and jaded than your average audience
because they've seen more right they see
10 times as much as they actually write
and publish and that means that if
you're going to them saying like oh did
you see that so and so said some dumb
stuff on the internet while our app
fixes that right or even worse some
natural disaster just happened guess
what our app it's like don't do that a
it's just poor taste but then B like I
don't think any writer has ever really
been tempted by that hook you know any
quality writer I think that's the last
thing I would do your subject line
keywords should however be geared
towards one or two levels up in the meta
of what's happening so you should be
cognizant of the world around us let's
say we pull you out a current affair
that would be interesting to pitch
around if you're Tech app this post zero
interest rate Universe if you have
something that appeals to a demographic
that may have been less likely to be
interested in it before when interest
rates were low let's say you are I'll
just pick one out of The Ether because I
like them I think they're cool but
co-pilot co-pilot took advantage of the
fact that and very straightforwardly and
non queasily took advantage of the fact
that mint was shut down by into it and
pilot had been building for a long time
this is obviously not something where
they're like o mint's going to get shut
down let me build this thing they have
existed they've been grinding it out I
use it I think it's a really cool app
for Personal Finance Management but
they' done the work however they were
ready they were on the balls of their
feet when mint was shut down they took
advantage of it by sharing doing a
little pitching I'm sure there was
organic stuff a lot people just said oh
what is the other good stuff out there
well they had done the work to make
their presence known and they had a
little bit of traction so you end up in
this position where you're able to
capitalize on this mint shutdown that's
a very organic current affairs news hook
type marketing plan at least marketing
reaction right they're a small team so
I'm sure it was not like let's gear up
the department it's like no all hands on
deck what do we need to do to take
advantage of this scenario and I think
they did that well I use a very similar
app Monarch money it's a fantastic one
as well so your co-pilot your Monarch
you were talking about you only see the
sub subject line so what's the subject
line they write that's going to get your
attention how do you tell that story in
in 10 words or less to get attention in
that subject line yeah it's like if
you're losing mint we're here to help if
you're going to go at it at the subject
line I think what you do is instead of
capitalizing or leaning into the shoden
fra of the situation or the negative
connotation oh mint sucked we're better
or oh so sad mince gone good thing we're
here instead it's like hey
this thing millions of people used over
the course of a decade is going away and
we know a lot of you are sort of
wondering what's next we are here to
help we think we're next we think we're
great Etc so confidence Clarity in your
mission we're here to help you manage
your finances we're here to step into
that Gap but no like reving in the
demise that's a restraint thing that is
hard for people to feel because in the
moment you want to like take advantage
of it and you are viewing it as an
entity because the fact is most people
realize if you're a m user early on you
realize they haven't really done
anything with that product in a long
time it hasn't gotten any better in any
material way it however was doing a job
for a lot of people still and it was
being maintained and there are still
people that work at Mid trying to keep
it running and the financial systems
connections require constant upkeep so
like there's no way that that app was
not being worked on so there's dozens if
not hundreds of people that are probably
out of a job now etc etc so You' got to
think through your second order effects
of your copy so if you're to go into
that thing with really leading into the
capitalizing on the shutdown angle then
you end up setting yourself up for
looking like a jerk saying like oh you
don't care about the people that just
lost their jobs or capitalizing on the
misfortune of people who maybe really
relied on mint to give them a snapshot
of their financial situation and are now
desperately looking for something new
and instead you're like hey it's really
unfortunate that such a pillar of the
community shut down but we've been
working on something we think is even
better so feel free to take a look at
what we've got here that's the way I
would position my thought process around
pitching that you want the attention you
got to capitalize on the moment that's a
given but doing it with style and with
restraint allows you the freedom in the
future to be like hey we were never an
antagonist in this space we were always
working alongside these other places to
try to do the job we're all trying to do
which is help you manage your finances
better our job is not to beat other
people it's to do a job for you
hopefully better than everybody else and
I think that's hard for some early stage
companies to modulate on that note while
I'm forcing you to live write pitches I
think this is another good kind of
example of that kind of opportunity in I
think it was this spring or last spring
apple weather was going down a bunch
there were actually a lot of posts about
like hey Apple weather's not reliable
anymore here are the apps to instead and
I actually have a weather app we hadn't
updated it so I didn't bother pitching
it but if I were in that moment with my
weather app how do I pitch like hey
Apple weather's going down use my app
instead how do you approach that without
throwing Apple under the bus these are
the kind of things that come up for app
developers where they've got a better
solution or things happen to other app
or things like that so how would you
pitch that without totally throwing
Apple into the bus there's two
components to that one is you have to
understand when you're punching up or
punching down this goes for journalism
as well writers often have issues with
this especially early in their career
you have to understand the weight that
you carry versus the weight that you are
pushing against Apple can handle it
right like in many ways like apple can
sort of take the abuse as an
organization now on an individual level
I'm sure the people that work on weather
weren't happy that it was breaking a lot
but it is a matter of General States and
I think if you evaluate every
scenario by that rule of not punching
down you can sometimes realize like hey
it's okay to get a little feisty with
our marketing when it comes to competing
with a company like apple which has
enormous resources to get the stuff
right they have essentially infinite
resources the fact that they work in
small teams does not absolve them from
the idea of having infrastructure that's
sound and that works well and they take
that seriously and the fact of the
matter is is that they should and so
calling them out or saying hey if you
went to Apple weather today and you got
a blank screen maybe it's time to look
at some other options is not necessarily
something where I would put it in that
same pocket of reveling in the demise of
an architecture that employs a lot of
people or that people have relied on for
a long time so I think it's actually
okay to get a little feistier when
you're dealing with the Giants literally
the biggest company on the planet
definitely biggest tech company
sometimes biggest company overall I
think it's harder to generate
empathy in audience or in yourself when
you're competing with that there's a
phenomenon I think where people will
capitalize on a moment in time and
create a marketing plan or create a
pitch around it but without any sort of
consideration of what happens after so
let's say Okay Apple weather's kind of
being wonky maybe it's been wonky for a
day and then the second day of outages
goes in you're like we're a weather app
why aren't we putting ourselves out
there as an alternative for people who
need a weather app right now you know
and you go and you make that plan and
you put it out there let's say your plan
is something like to Riff on the idea
that Apple weather isn't there but we're
there for you we still have all of this
stuff we have all the information you
need to decide whether or not you're
wearing a coat or whether or not your
job site is going to be muddy today and
whatever right the second order
ramifications of weather is what you're
playing on right like what do you need
and then you make that whole marketing
plan around that but what happens when
Apple weather comes back up and it's
really strong again what stops people
from moving away from you and back to
Apple weather because they like your
whole pitch was they're not there we are
okay well they came back so why you
right and so I think instead you really
have to go to this order of Apple
weather is down so we're going to use
that as an opportunity to Market
ourselves but the marketing really
should not be around Apple weather being
down and us being up instead it should
be around why our experience and feature
set is better than Apple weather at any
time you're the moment that they're down
to push into that Gap and push into
keywords being on the rise and the
searches being on the rise and all of
the pattern matching and registration is
aligning and spiking Search terms are
spiking and your attribution
opportunities are arising your keyword
marketing opportunities are rising up
all that's great step into that Gap but
instead of stepping in with the message
that like haha they're down we're not
you step in with a message that like hey
they're down did you know we offer like
all of these really cool features that
Apple weather doesn't mainly because
they have a focused experience and we
have on that single app and they're
doing so many things but this is all we
do this is all we care about we care
about weather weather weather all the
way down Apple cares about weather for 5
minutes out of a year metaphorically
speaking and we all we do is care about
this and so here's all the features and
things that you've been missing from
that experience that just happens to be
down right now and I think that that's
the way you do it because on the other
end of that marketing push on the other
end of all those users the churn is
mitigated by the fact that those users
came in through a pipeline of
understanding the differentiation
factors not just the needs in the moment
of an app that was up while another one
was down and I think that that's like a
key strategic mistake that a lot of
companies make especially early on is
that they view targets of opportunity as
moments to win in the moment but they
don't consider the ramifications
Downstream like if your marketing has
been preaching that you're really good
because X Y or Z other external not
internal but external factor is in place
weather being down mint being shut down
those are externalities the
internalities are we're really good
we're welld designed we're a pleasure to
use we can serve you well those
internalities are the things that will
keep your users there and keep them from
turning back out when Apple weather
comes back up or even when the next
keynote announces one more feature for
Apple weather it keeps them from
churning out cuz they're like oh yeah
but I have all these features that I was
pitched on marketed on as I was coming
into this thing they're still there I
still use them and they're still great
and I think that's a huge misstep that a
lot of people make because they're so
anxious to take advantage of the moment
they think that the moment is the
marketing when in fact the moment is
just the moment and the marketing should
be the same story that you've been
telling about yourself and your benefits
the apps benefits to the user the whole
time and will tell into the future I
want to get back into pitching in a bit
but I did want to step back to the first
question we started on which was
understanding what it's like to be a
journalist in
2023 and as you alluded to there's so
many more pitches so much more news how
did you at Tech crunch as editorinchief
decide how to balance the breaking news
the this company rais this amount of
money this app did this I mean there's
so many potential topics to write about
help us understand that thought process
for a writer of like what is actually
worth covering when could technically
write 10,000 posts a day and potentially
all of them be fairly interesting it's
like you have to prioritize so how does
a newsroom kind of approach that in 2023
yeah I don't want to pretend that
there's some sort of magical equilibrium
that I ever was able to achieve you are
always balancing those needs the needs
of the audience to hear new information
for you to you know scoop new
information that was previously unknown
for you to serve an existing Audience by
covering the things that you know they
already want and then certain percentage
of it that is about keeping yourself
from getting burnt out by covering
things that you want to cover you just
go like this is personally interesting
to me and honestly those stories tend to
be the most potent and valuable and
interesting long term especially for
early stage companies like you convert
somebody into a Believer a believer in
the thing that you're doing the thing
that you're trying to accomplish the
mission that you have and those writers
will become sort of chroniclers of your
progress over time if you're able to
capture one or two of those folks
everybody else is targets of opportunity
but you're able to sort of get into the
minds and hearts of individual writers
at a publication it's so much more
valuable than oh we got covered by
publication X it really is about getting
covered by writer why and that is
because they have an audience that they
are trying to intentionally build and
it's just like anything else like why do
you advertise on Google instead of
advertising on the street well Google
has aggregated an audio audience
intentionally for this purpose and like
that writer is doing a lot of the same
work not for the same reasons but really
to the same end which is they want a
portable audience that comes with them
wherever they go they want people to
understand that they are an authority on
a particular subject and because that
begets new stories they're able to
generate sourcing in a particular
Universe build a Rolodex in that
Universe understand it really well so
that when you come along pitching an app
that happens to exist in that universe
let's say laundry as a service or
whatever you're pitching they're like
hey I've covered laundry for a decade
like I know this I can pull together my
priors to help me to understand how they
are actually trying to make a change
here or make an impact here and if they
have all of that pre-existing knowledge
of the space you're going to get
somebody that's approaching it in a more
intelligent way in a more understanding
way you're going to get a deeper story a
richer Story one that has more meat to
it and one that frankly will be more
useful to you down the line if you are
in the Venture back space it can become
an easy way to replace sending your
pitch deck you say hey check out this
story that so and so wrote about us I
think it captures pretty well what we
want to do and if you want to know more
I'm happy to dive in and let you know
what our progress has been since then
Etc but I've had plenty of people tell
me personally and I know other writers
have the same experience in the past
where they're like hey we pitched you
you really got it from the beginning you
wrote a great story on it it wasn't like
the story was universally positive it
pointed out some of the things the
challenges that we had we thought it was
fair and we just stopped sending our
deck and started sending the story and
we raised essentially off of your story
because it was an idea that here's
somebody who is a student of that thing
of that space and they are essentially
taking on the role of an outside board
member and saying like here are the
challenges I think you're going to come
up against these are the things that
really would be interesting if they did
in the future here's what they're trying
to do now here are the founders and
their story and why they seem to be the
right team to tackle this and if you're
able to get that kind of story it could
become a pretty lynchpin moment and I'm
not being like agonizing here there are
other ways to chart your course than
getting one great story but I have had
that told to me over and over and over
and over over the years that if you have
somebody external that really believes
in it and is a good storyteller and
manages to tell the story in that way
even if it's not like every word is
something you love maybe they're
critiquing things about it or whatever
you end up with a Believer outside and
that helps boost morale it boosts your
ability to tell that message and say
we're not just speaking our book
somebody else sees what we're trying to
do and that can be really helpful yeah I
think that's a really good point is
don't just in andatee all the tips email
boxes but actually go look for the
writer so if you want Tech crunch to
cover your app you need to know know
who's the fintech rider who at Tech
crunch cares about weather apps who at
Tech crunch cared about mint because the
example we were giving earlier like
you're going to land that pitch better
if you're pitching the person who
actually cares about personal finance
versus pitching a broader story I guess
there's some amount of the mainline tips
email gets distributed if there is
something interesting your hit rate's
going to be higher if you know the
person actually cares about what you're
doing and then craf your pitch more
individualistic like hey I know you've
written about personal finance in the
past and those sorts of things I think
get missed often in just this spray and
prey approach to PR versus that kind of
more nuanced and crafting a message and
then I think that audience site fit is
also important like Tech crunch is not
the place to pitch certain things and
like the tech crunch audience doesn't go
to Tech crunch I mean it's a good thing
for you to chime in on like how do you
view the tech crunch audience and what
they care about versus some of these
pitches you get where it's a cool app
but you're like eh it's just not what
the tech crunch audience is coming to
TechCrunch for this would be better for
95 Mac or Mac Rumors or somebody who
covers the kind of Enthusiast side of
things more how do you think about that
there are a lot of reasons people read
any site so I don't like to
overgeneralize because I've seen just
how granular it can get from an audience
perspective and how you have to sort of
play the keyboard and really touch
different tempos for different people on
a day-to-day basis but I can say with
some Authority that some of the major
reasons people read Tech wrench there
really three kind of major reasons
Market intelligence like what are
competitors doing what's happening in
the space what are people investing in
who are they investing in and is this
somebody I should Target because I'm in
a similar space the second is recruiting
so very simply we want people to join us
so if we can get a story told about what
we're trying to do how hard it is how
hard the problem is how interesting it
is ETC we can then use that as
recruiting tool and then raising money
if we're able to get a story there we
can then use that to raise money or get
attention set us apart from the rest of
the industry the thousands of companies
that are pitching investors because you
think our inboxes are in that dat
investors in boxes are 10 times worse
right on an individual basis they're not
we get it all but I get an aggregate
investors in boxes are very full too so
those are kind of like the major reasons
so if somebody has got an app and
they're not doing any of those things it
is the fourth reason that anybody
pitches anybody anywhere just why I
didn't really include it in the primary
Tech crunch bucket is user acquisition
so you want to pitch so that people
download and use your app our audience
is very specific in that regard so when
we post on an app it often gets
thousands of new users that is not
unusual sometimes tens of thousands in
rare cases hundreds of thousands of new
users over the course of several weeks
that the article stays in high
circulation and you know obviously
there's exceptions where Evergreen
articles feature a particular app and
that app still tells us man we still get
people signing up from there and that's
great it's all lovely it's sort of the
reason you put an app out there in the
first place as a writer you're like I
found it interesting so if other people
find it interesting that's a win right
for you like you don't really I'm going
to use the term very Loosely here so
forgive me but you don't care if they
get users or not but it's nice because
you cared in the first place you cared
to write about it so then the followon
effect of them getting users feels good
cuz you're like cool I cared about it
enough other people cared about it
that's my job that part of it is fun but
the user acquisition thing is very
targeted so like if you're looking at
that being your primary goal you're not
raising you're not recruiting a bunch of
people like you're hiring maybe one or
two almost always hopefully if you're
growing looking at maybe bringing on
some additional help to help you grow
but your primary use case is like okay
user acquisition I really think that
user acquisition that Target for this
much better suited to things like Tik
Tok install ads or Facebook install ads
or attribution on Google or whatever the
case may be like that should be your
user acquisition strategy for the
long-term broad base scattershot however
your pinpoint user acquisition like
acquiring certain users certain kinds of
users then pitching a particular
publication becomes very useful so it's
not like I'm going to get a million
users just because I got an article on
tick crunch but you may get a few
thousand users of a very specific type
like early adopters power users people
that are very likely to give you
feedback people that are very likely to
like email you personally and be like
hey I noticed this thing was broken
there's lots of really interesting
cross-section of people Builders
creators Engineers investors people that
take a very
particular high intensity interest in
apps and in in companies that they see
on our site and I think that that is
very useful at certain points in your
growth career in your growth trajectory
so whereas the longtail may feel a
little different the near term it could
be very strategically important and
interesting to Target certain sites and
on that topic of posts that do sometimes
get 100,000 views or whatever how much
in 2023 are writer still thinking like
how much traction is this post goingon
to get like how important is that and I
know that's going to vary publication to
publication but speaking from your
experience at Tech grunch and you know
all the friends you have in journalism
how much are you thinking like well I
don't really want to cover this because
I doubt it's going to get much traction
like is that still something you're
thinking about day in day out yes You'
be a liar to say that that wasn't a
concern that was always floating in your
head because the cascading set of goals
is that the publisher defines a growth
goal the editor has to figure out a way
to generate the traffic to contribute to
that goal or other Revenue aspects that
involve editorial anything related to
that whether it's traffic or in our case
events programming or other things like
that from an editorial perspective and
of course it Cascades down from there if
you have managers or editorial desk
managers or managing editors or whatever
and then down to the writers at some
point it's going to Cascade down and
that writer is going to understand that
the overall goals of the publication
hopefully in a nice good way where they
feel like I want to contribute to this
goal I want us to win that's great at a
lot of Publications I understand it is
not that Pleasant and it is much more
specific like you have traffic goals of
x amount and where are the posts that
are generating that and you know I want
these out now and we need to generate
traffic X Y or Z now that's
understandable these are businesses
editorial business is still a business
we handle things differently I think
than a lot of other news Orcs because we
were extremely always were extremely
transparent with our writers about where
we were in terms of goal setting why we
were going there where you're headed
it's just my leadership style to try to
operate from consensus rather than
mandate rather than saying like you will
do X it's here's what we want to
accomplish and then back into the and
then therefore I really need you to do X
and that's I think has been helpful
you'd have to talk to my former
employees but I think it has been
helpful in like keeping people around
for a lot longer than a lot of other
orgs or at least happier at their jobs
but the fact is that every writer every
day has a story selection job to do that
that's their primary job it's not it's
not any of the other things everything
else Cascades from there they have to
select stories to pursue right sometimes
that comes from a source that tips them
off to a thing and then they're like I'm
going to pursue this because this is
unknown information I'm going to pursue
it sometimes it's from a pitch
somebody's like I have this app I really
think you'd love it given everything
that you write about I convinced that
you'd love it you're like okay cool I'll
bite right what is it like that's a
story selection choice and those choices
are always predicated on the fact that
like will this push the overall or
towards its goals and that in many ways
is traffic so if you're writing
therefore ipof facto if you are writing
about something that nobody's ever heard
of you have to be very convinced that
you're going to be able to tell that
story in a way that's going to capture
brought attention and translate that
into traffic or you're going to have to
say this one goes in the column of I
think it's important that we write about
this now so that we look really smart
later or this will turn into a larger
story later on or we'll be able to
follow this down the course of its
becoming a much larger thing that more
people care about and I think that's the
sweet spot for Tech runch is that we
always wanted to be super early to stuff
12 to 18 months early to things so that
by the time it made it to the pages of
the times or the journal or anything
like that people could go look at the
history of the company on Tech wrench
they could go what did the founders say
about the company like three weeks after
he started the company to Tech wrench
that's an important thing because it
keeps people honest we definitely have a
lot of company history and I always told
my people that in some ways we are
writing the history of silic and Valley
in real time and so like if you're able
to go back onto the pages of TC and see
an early an app covered very early
before anybody knew who the founder was
or maybe there was their first company
and now they're a Serial founder big wck
or something like that but you could see
the story of it and what they were
saying about it and why they founded it
and all that stuff so our writers had
the remit to balance those needs to
about broad interest stories about
companies like Apple or Google or big
names that almost anybody be interested
in some move they were making but put it
in the context of the startup Universe
oh Apple farted what does this fart mean
for your business what does it mean for
a developer trying to generate its own
fart that's an important distinction you
know about the way that we covered stuff
it wasn't just like oh Apple did X it's
like apple did X and here's what it
means for you and for our audience for
our particular Universe I think a lot of
sites out there their primary job is
just to recount and announce the things
that Apple has done which is fine if
that's your job if that's your remit and
you are an Enthusiast site for an
Enthusiast audience great there's no
shame in that that's your thing like a
lot of people are busy they work all day
whenever they come home they're like I
can just open 95 Mac and scroll and see
the cool stuff that's happened or I can
open Mac rumors and see if new hardware
is going to be launching and like they
got their calendar and I can kind of
make a buying decision those are all
genuine user driven services for us
given our universe our service that we
were providing is like Oh I'm a
developer we're a young company there's
three of us we're trying to make X
happen and apple just announced a thing
that we can take advantage of to maybe
get us to the next level I really want
to understand that thing I want to
understand what it's about I want to get
a perspective of a certain writer as you
mentioned because I know that they
understand the space really well and if
this writer tells me this is actually
kind of a dead end and most of the apis
you would want to use to take advantage
of this or private still so don't get
too excited I'm gonna be like okay cool
we can modulate we don't have to like
pivot and like put all of our
engineering resources on implementing
this if we understand that it's still
nent and Apple's like we'll do something
cool with this in two years we can take
our time or whatever that application of
engineering resources business decision
making from an inuring perspective or
from a true business perspective
monetary perspective like those things
we've felt were like important duties
but at the same time you have to also be
doing the work of finding the new stuff
putting the gashes on and waiting out
into the swamp and picking and holding
these things up to the light because
that is the job that we provide the core
readership the people that sit down at
their desk and open a tab and the tab
defaults to De Crush right like we had
to service that audience of hundreds of
thousands of people that read us every
single day that idea of balancing those
was always a huge point of stress like
you carry that in your lumbar because
you have to satisfy the needs to grow
and the revenue needs of the
organization but you also have to
satisfy the innate job that you're doing
for the audience especially the most
loyal audience and make sure that you're
not giving up one for the other you
can't just be all pigeon hole all the
time or all rabbit hole all the time
because then you'll end up not getting
any new audience at all but you also
can't go fully broad because then the
core audience is like you don't do this
job for me anymore that you used to do I
can get this broad stuff elsewhere too
and your unique perspective isn't enough
I need the unique perspective and then I
also need the brand new that Balancing
Act is tough yeah to kind of circle back
to pitching understanding this about
tech crunch I think will help folks
understand how to pitch Tech Crunch and
this is why I wanted to have you on and
this all may be changing just so
everybody knows
I'm no longer in chart but I will say a
lot of the writers individually at tC
have always appreciated individual
pitching and I know writers other
Publications do too they tell me every
day and I'm sure they tell you if you
know their work and you follow their
work and you know they'd be interested
and fascinated in that that is going to
be a far more effective pitch than the
most clever subject line that you could
write that gets blasted out to everybody
and so when you're going to pitch Vogue
you understand what Vogue carries and
Carries about and why they care about
your fashion app when you're going to
pitch the Verge you need to understand
what the Verge cares about what those
Riders care about what their job to be
done in the broader Cress ecosystem is
and like you said 9o5 Max's a great
place for new app developers to pitch
because they do a ton of stories and so
you can understand okay if we're
pitching nin to-5 Mac they just care
more about hey this is a new app and
they're less focused on that broader
storytelling of writing the history of
Silicon Valley than Tech crunch is so
when you pi check crunch you need to be
thinking about that kind of Storytelling
and when you pitched nin to-5 back you
don't send them the same pitch that you
sent to the riter at Tech crunch you
send them a totally different pitch and
to be most effective at this you you
really do need to understand and think
about those perspectives I think it was
really helpful for you to share that
perspective everybody thinks TechCrunch
is the ultimate place to get my app
covered or business covered whatever
because it is that history of Silicon
Valley the paper record for the tech
industry if you will but sometimes you
got to tell the right story if you're
actually going to get coverage so let's
talk a little bit more about that we
kind of used two hypotheticals with mint
going down and then Apple Weather
Service having issues but what are some
other ways and stories that you think an
app Business should be pitching Tech
crunch specifically and then maybe more
broadly that will register with the
writers will register with the broader
audience given the how crowded the app
space is I think it's really important
for you to tell stories that they're
going to focus on differentiation
factors almost exclusively in other
words I think a lot of times especially
in early days you get so wrapped up in
all the work that you've done to build
out like the basis for this thing that
you're creating that you get really
enamored with it as you should you
should be really pleased with all of
your work you should be really happy
because otherwise why are you doing it
like you should be really excited about
the fact that it exists and that the
company exists and that it has employees
and that it has a product and that it's
on the app store or or about to be and
you should be really proud of all the
fundamentals that you've built in maybe
you've done work with accessibility
maybe you've done work with design that
you're really proud of maybe you've done
work with some base cleverness of your
approach but in all reality all that
stuff is sort of assumed like we
wouldn't even be looking at your pitch
or at your idea or concept or whatever
if those things weren't already met the
bar is just higher now existing does not
mean anything congratulations and I'm
not being rude or crude about it but it
doesn't mean anything it's like the old
saying that ideas are worthless ideas
are worthless that Still Remains true to
today let's put it this very
specifically ideas are worthless in
company building because if you do not
execute on those ideas if you don't
build those ideas if you don't make
those ideas real they're worth zero
right which is why somebody's like I
have an idea for an app congratulations
you have nothing that remains True to
this day however I would say the bar is
even higher now which is that solid
design that uses at a base level Apple's
fairly robust design Frameworks and UI
Frameworks that they provided you know
the bone stock stuff looks pretty good
these days that uses those basic frames
or Google like if you're launching on
the Android store Google has a really
solid set of design language and a solid
set of UI elements now that I think 10
years ago definitely didn't exist it
even 5 years ago wasn't that great but I
think in the last few years we've gotten
to a really solid place where there's no
excuse for you not to come with like a
really solid game on all those fronts
but then once you reach that point you
have to realize that you've just reached
zero and so like from there it is what
you're doing in service of your mission
that sets you apart like that
differentiation in execution or
onboarding or feature use or set of
circumstances that is really going to
allow you to catch the eye of a reporter
or catch the eye of someone the
cleverness that exists above and beyond
the table Stakes or what is going to set
it apart that is I think sometimes a
hard realization for a lot of people
because they get into this place where
they've been so close to it for so long
that they're like we did all of these
things really really well that's great
so do a lot of people I'm just gonna
give you rough percentages here so if we
get pitched by 500 people in a day not
unusual for any writer you get pitched
by 500 people in a day 100 of those
people have really done the work to just
put something together that looks like
it actually is a real company out of
those hundred maybe a dozen are even in
your space that dozen have done the job
of like actually pitching you correctly
like and saying like Hey we're real but
also we're really interesting to you
we're not just real and interesting to
someone like we're real and interesting
to you as a writer and out of those
dozen you are then forced with this
forcing function of okay what is the
unique bits out of these and I'm
exaggerating here because it doesn't
always come in clumps like this but
let's say those dozen you're a fintech
writer and all of those dozen are
fintech companies and all of those dozen
look legit they've done the work to have
a solidly designed app that seems to
have some user affordances that are cool
and that looks like they've done the
work and so out of those which of those
has the interesting hook of that
additional percentage above zero whether
that's a really cleverly designed
feature taking advantage of a a freshly
launched new sensor or feature of a
platform like Apple or Google or
somebody else's shipped is addressing a
need in the current environment we
talked about post earlier but other
environments can be like Co was a good
example obviously of many people
capitalizing on that I don't even really
think it matters if I'm talking about
something that exists right now because
people may watch this and it may be
different a week from now well like open
AI launches a new model you've utilized
that new model in a clever way you've
got a new feature threads that tie into
the overall stories that that writer has
been covering or that the industry or
audience is interested in and then I
think the big elephant in the room that
we haven't talked about yet and that I
think can be very interesting if it's
done right is the story of the people
that have built this thing so you have
to reach to zero you have to get to zero
first you have to have a thing that
exists that's really well built that
seems clever that seems like it's
tackling an interesting problem and then
you can start telling personal stories
my brother and I founded this app my
sister and I founded this app we saw a
need because our mother was in hospice
and there was no Elder Care app that
also integrated message in this way so
that we could check up on her quality of
care every day you know with a few
simple Taps Etc and like those kinds of
opportunities I think are ones that
allow you to do that storytelling above
and beyond but you have to hit zero
first I think that's a really good point
that even in the storytelling like oh my
sister and I created this app because
our mom was in hospice that's part of a
story but you still have to tell a story
of like why does it matter and did you
do something unique cuz if there's
there's a hundred other apps that do the
same thing your personal story of why
you created it doesn't matter as much as
it actually doing something and so I
think that was a great framing it's like
you got to get to zero like it's got to
be a good functional well-built app
there's just such a high Baseline now
but then you really do need to do
something above and beyond and I think
this applies to marketing generally as
well is just that you need to focus on
that differentiation and if you're not
doing something new and unique and
exciting and help
what are you doing and so getting to
zero and building that stuff on top and
then telling those stories is then what
gives you the authority to then tell
more stories about why and how and
things like that so that's a really good
framing changing gears a little bit how
effective do you think PR agencies are
these days at helping folks tell those
stories and how effective are PR
agencies at working with the press these
days do you recommend working with
somebody to help craft those stories or
is it maybe something a Founder should
just get really good at themselves and
take that onetoone approach there is a
service provided by good I prefis by
saying let's say you managed to identify
a solid PR firm with good reputation
that seem very attentive to your needs
and understanding of where you are in
your course of existence as a company
there are definitely services that they
provide that you're trading money for
time with a lot of those agencies and
they're doing the work of like packaging
press kits and offering up services that
allow you to pitch a broad number of
Publications or a broad number of media
or come up with that but I think that
honestly strategy based comms and
marketing is so much more interesting
and so much more important longterm I
think a lot of people get into this
thing like okay we need somebody to make
press releases and send press releases
and write those and Pitch people on our
behalf all that's fine and I think it
can work for certain classes of company
and app so like for an app that is
interested in garnering the largest
possible pitch surface area that goes
across hundreds or thousands of I don't
know let's say gaming blocks right like
let's say you're a game that has a
relatively quasi predatory inap purchase
scenario and your job is to get it out
to hundreds or dozens of sites that can
just get it into circulation so that
your SEO and therefore attribution and
acquisition strategies across Google and
Facebook are aided by that you want like
the purest form of PR Company right
which is like generating press releases
pitching it to thousands of sites
managing that flow and all of that stuff
because you don't have the time for it
these are not people that are doing CEO
interviews or in-depth explorations of
the rationale behind their app they just
want the name of the app out there the
fact that it exists the fact that it has
a few screenshots that are interesting
and has a link to download it they want
to seed that into the universe in a way
that is one step above completely
inorganic acquisition which would just
be them placing ads that's one step
above that but I think several steps
several layers above that is the idea
that you have a strategist that works
with you to generate a strategy around
your story like the story that you're
trying to tell how you're trying to tell
it the narrative that you're building
over time that your users now and in the
future will always recognize as true the
story you've always been telling you
won't get that out of a PR firm you
really need to get that out of a PR
strategist you mentioned one of the
services that PR agencies can help with
is prits and things like that I know
it's something that's actually really
important for somebody pitching to
consider is to make it as easy as
possible on the writer to write the
story any tips on how to make that super
easy so we've talked crafting a good
pitch you've got their attention but now
they have to do the work how do you make
that easy and more compelling for them
to tell that story if you want to talk
about like mechanical Baseline pragmatic
stuff that you can do to help make sure
that your pitch is more well received
short simple straight to the point
subject lines a couple of lines of body
copy don't inundate because most of that
stuff won't get read especially if it
feels like it's been pasted in which
inevitably it will because if you're
pasting something in there why should I
read a paste I want to read a couple of
simple sentences from you about why your
thing is unique why it's interesting if
you have a very defining potent
straightforward screenshot of something
that's in your app you're like look we
did this it's really cool you're going
to love it put that in there too write
in the body of the email and then most
writers
if they have any sort of opsc will not
have images loading automatically so
it's no harm no foul it'll load just as
fast you don't have to worry about it
the image will be collapsed and then
they can always click on view image if
they want to right but just from the
nature of protecting against viruses and
tracking pixels and anything else most
writers have images hidden by default by
the way if you can avoid on any
individual pitch I would never include
tracking pixels or links it's just sort
of a matter of respect now I understand
completely if you're doing a campaign or
a broad pitch you need those right we
everybody understands everybody gets it
but if you're doing individual pitch
don't do like read receipts or tracking
pixels inside emails and especially
never ever call them on oh you I saw you
open by email creepy it's really weird
that's not going to do anything if you
want to like email them say hey I didn't
know if you got my email great you know
what I mean fine okay we understand
persistence and followup up although at
some point chill the tracking stuff do
away with that and then you can always
attach the press kit and attaching the
press kit with high resolution images or
just providing a link to it depending on
the service that you're using with high
resolution images all the information
they could ever want about the founders
their backstory the app its purpose and
then the images or assets necessary in a
link or tucked away in an attachment but
leaving the main copy as a place for you
to tell your personal story a few
sentences I think is the most effective
pitches that I've seen or that way we've
given you all the resources that you
need to write the story if you find it
compelling without any additional
Outreach however we're here if you need
us feel free email me directly I'll
answer right away whatever here's my
direct email here's my phone number
whatever you feel comfortable with as a
Founder as a app creator but whatever
direct connection you can provide is
always good text me at whatever if you
have any questions things like that
because oftentimes writers are under
crazy deadlines they're trying to move
fast getting a quick response could mean
the difference between them writing that
story that day or maybe it gets pushed
to the next day if they don't get a
response and then Instagram sells for a
billion dollars and they don't write
about you anymore right because they're
busy with other things and so you want
to provide the most lubrication possible
but you also don't want the body of the
copy to read like a Facebook ad or to
feel cluttered with all this information
that's overwhelming just keep it simple
I think that that's fantastic advice and
it's something I probably haven't done
good at over the years with my presskits
specifically is that I've kept my
pitches pretty tight but I've also kept
my presskits maybe a little too tight so
you're saying the best thing is to have
that really tight pitch but once they
click you want to give them as much
resource but organized well easy to read
you still want to craft that in a way
that makes it easy on them but to just
give them all the resources where they
don't have to interview you to
understand parts of the story like they
could just jump to that press kit they
have everything they need images details
list list of features like that's where
you put the depth because you've already
got their attention right yeah I think
so I think that's a really
straightforward standard tactic the one
thing you do want to avoid is attempting
to write the story for the writer so if
you're like including a section let's
say on bios let's say you feel that your
founder story is really strong you've
got a set of strong Founders we
mentioned that brother and sister
earlier that had a compelling story
about their mother in hospice and wrote
this app to facilitate communication and
standards of care and all that stuff a
couple of lines about that is great but
you don't want to go too in depth
because it doesn't leave any room for
the writer to tell a story if you have a
really compelling founder story and
you've explained it enough in a few
sentences so that they understand it
that will be enough and then you offer
the communication so that they can then
communicate with you do any additional
interviewing and tease that story out
and draw it out that feels good what
doesn't feel good as a writer is
somebody having pitched to what they
view as the story pre-written in quotes
maybe not a full story pre-written
although I have seen that it's so funny
um but like a story about them you want
to tease them with your story I've got a
really compelling story XY I think is
really cool but then let them go wait
really like how did that happen how did
it come about you know pulling out the
details from there so when I say details
you want enough detail in there to offer
them teasers of why the story is
interesting and then of course
mechanically speaking you know like app
store listings and descriptions and
screenshots all of that stuff so that
you don't have to like manually go to
the App Store to pull screenshots or
anything like that and of course test
flight links or links to download the
app if it's live just to make sure that
they have access to it and direct access
they don't go searching for it all the
mechanical stuff that I'm sure everybody
knows but I think that's super important
to include you know and I think that's
maybe a good framing then is that don't
write the story but provide the building
blocks for them to write the story
awesome well I think this has been super
helpful to dig into all the thinking
behind how something goes from Pitch to
actually landing on Tech Crunch and how
to tell the right stories and I think so
much of this applies to marketing more
broadly pitching influencers creating
your copy for advertising all those kind
of things everything we talked about
applies to that as well but as we wrap
up anything else you wanted to share I
really had a nice time talking about
this stuff I mean I think there is a
high amount of noise but signal still
pokes through and those ones that poke
through typically are so much more fun
to write about and interesting and I
think if you have an interesting
compelling story you know it's truly
differentiated it's not a shell game
that it's basically like another vehicle
that's very similar to anything else out
there but you think you've got a unique
story but you really don't I think
you're going to win out attention
somewhere persistence does pay off
people are very very very busy it's very
intense out there so don't lose heart
you will find a way to punch through
it's not a function of you I think it's
very important for Founders to
understand from a mental health
perspective and a frustration
perspective it's very very very unlikely
that it is anything about you personally
or about some competitor though that got
covered and you didn't it is generally a
byproduct of it just being extremely
noisy out there these days so he B it
stay persistent all right thanks so much
Matthew it's great having you on today
no problem David thank you very
much thanks so much for listening if you
have a minute please leave a review in
your favorite podcast player you can
also stop by chat. sub club.com to join
our private
[Music]
community